Guide to the Milton R. Konvitz Collections 1936-2017
Konvitz, Milton R., Collections
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Milton R. Konvitz Collections, 1936-2017
/4341
Konvitz, Milton R.; Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives
297 linear ft.
Records (documents), correspondence, papers (documents).
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Professor Konvitz's files regarding the drawing up of the official body of statutory laws for the Republic of Liberia.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
March 12, 1908-September 5, 2003 Milton Konvitz, a Cornell University faculty member and authority on constitutional and labor law, and civil and human rights, died Sept. 5 at the age of 95. Konvitz was a founding faculty member in the School of Industrial and Labor Relations from 1946 until his retirement in 1973. He was also a professor in Cornell's Law School. Konvitz is perhaps best known for his American Ideals course, which he taught to more than 8,000 students over the course of his career, never giving the same lecture twice. "I saw the U.S. Constitution as it has been interpreted as a magnificent depository of our ideals, both individual and social," he said. His course exposed students to the great intellectual thinkers and philosophers throughout history whose writings had shaped those ideals. They included Sophocles, whose play Antigone is Cornell's New Student Reading Project this year. One student he influenced was U.S. Supreme Court Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Cornell Class of 1954, who considers him a mentor. At Cornell Konvitz also was a founder of the university's Department of Near Eastern Studies and Program of Jewish Studies. "I felt it was essential for a college interested in the humanities not to leave out Hebrew language and literature," he said. "And the knowledge of Jewish history, which began 4,000 years ago and has contributed to civilization no less than Greek, Roman or English history, is important to today's students-Jewish and non-Jewish." He often hosted students at his Ithaca home and helped start the first Kosher dining option at Cornell, Young Israel House. In addition, for nearly 30 years he directed the Liberian Codification Project, which drew up the official body of statutory laws that is still in force in the Republic of Liberia today, despite the current political upheaval there. Konvitz also edited the opinions of Liberia's Supreme Court and received the Grand Band of the Order of the Star of Africa, the highest award given to foreigners, as well as an honorary degree from the University of Liberia, one of seven honorary degrees he received in his lifetime. Active as a scholar and writer until his death, he wrote books and articles on American constitutional law that won him wide recognition and were cited in U.S. Supreme Court opinions. Among his nine books is Fundamental Liberties of a Free People: Religion, Speech, Press, Assembly, which was republished earlier this year with an expanded introduction by him that is strongly critical of the Rehnquist Supreme Court. Other books include A Century of Civil Rights (1983) and Judaism and Human Rights (2nd ed. 2001). He also edited a dozen volumes, including two on American philosopher Ralph Waldo Emerson, whose thinking shaped his views. One Emersonian idea he absorbed was that readers give life to books, which Konvitz recast as follows: "It is in their hearing that students bring life to the words, the thoughts, the teacher." Konvitz was born in Safed, Palestine (now Israel ), in 1908, the son of a rabbi. He immigrated to the United States in 1915 and became a naturalized citizen in 1926. He received a bachelor's degree in 1929 and a law degree in 1930, both from New York University, and a Ph.D. in philosophy from Cornell in 1933. Before joining Cornell's faculty, he was one of three assistant general counsels to Thurgood Marshall at the NAACP Legal Defense Fund for three years. He is survived by his wife, Mary, of Oakhurst, N.J.; a brother, Phillip, of Elberon, N.J.; a son and daughter-in-law, Josef and Isa, of Paris, France; and two grandsons, Eli and Ezra. Josef Konvitz, who grew up in Ithaca, is now an official at the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Boxes 1-3, 8-12, and 15-31 of this collection were transferred to the Cornell Law Library in 2005. Please consult with the Law Library Reference Librarian for these additional materials.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Konvitz, Milton R.(Milton Ridvas), 1908-2003; Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations.
Form and Genre Terms:
Records (documents).; Correspondence; Papers (documents)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
RELATED MATERIALS
Related Collections:
/4289 AV: ILR School Alumni Affairs and Development Audio-Visual Materials
/4297: ILR School Biography Files
6047: Archives Information File
CONTAINER LIST
- /3033: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Project Files (Box 1, Folder 1)
  4 linear feet. Professor Konvitz's files regarding the drawing up of the official body of statutory laws for the Republic of Liberia.
- /4039: Milton R. Konvitz Papers (Box 1, Folder 2)
  204.8 linear feet
- /4039 AV: Milton R. Konvitz American Ideals Lectures Audio-Visual Materials, 1973- 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  10.6 linear feet
- /4039 B: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers, 1936-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  6.3 linear feet
- /4039 L: Milton R. Konvitz Liberian Codification Project, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  6 linear feet. Boxes 1-3, 8-12, and 15-31 of this collection were transferred to the Cornell Law Library in 2005. Please consult with the Law Library Reference Librarian for these additional materials.
- /4039m: Milton R. Konvitz Tribute to Irving M. Ives and Edmund Ezra Day, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  1 file folder
- /4085: Milton R. Konvitz Additional Papers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  58 linear feet
- /4220m: Milton Konvitz Additional Papers, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  1 file folder.
- /4241: Milton Konvitz Personal Correspondence, 1941-2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  2.5 linear feet.
- /4242 AV: Milton Konvitz Memorial Service Audio-Visual Materials, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  4 CDs and 1 video cassette
- /4315 G: ILR School Milton Konvitz Memorial Posters, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  0.7 linear feet
- 6957 PUBS: Inauguration de la Collection Milton R. Konvitz, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  1 bound volume